today we're going to begin our study in
the history of philosophy
in a brief overview of Aurelius
Augustine who is known to us more
commonly is Saint Augustine or some
people mimicking the name of the city in
Florida call him Saint Augustine
it's been said of Augustine that he is
the greatest Theologian at least of the
first Millennium of Christian history if
not in the entire history of the church
but he distinguished himself not only
for his work in theology but also in the
realm of philosophy
and as a bishop being the
Bishop in in the early Church in North
Africa
and also as a founder of a monastic
order that bears his name
and certainly it would not be an
overstatement to say that no one in the
first thousand years of church history
had such a formative influence on
Christian thinking as this man did and
part of the thing that is so important
and understanding Augustine is that he
didn't have the advantage as anselmed
dead and August or his Aquinas did and
later Lutheran Calvin and Edwards did of
having had an Augustine to go before
them
he was on his own more or less he was
the
pioneering intellectual giant of the
early Christian centuries
we also see that in Augustine he perhaps
more than any single figure
gave definition to the soteriology or
the doctrines of salvation that Define
historic reformed theology and
protestantism so that Protestants all
claim Augustine as their father while at
the same time his definition of the
nature and function of the church that
is his development of ecclesiology the
doctrine of the church
has had a tremendous impact on the
development of Roman Catholic
ecclesiology so that the Roman Church
also claims Augustine for their own and
much of the debate in the 16th century
during the Reformation was the debate
about where Augustine fit in the whole
scheme of things of that time now
Augustine was born in the fourth Century
in the middle of 4th Century in the year
354 and died in the year 430.
and during the course of his life he was
engaged in many many theological and
philosophical controversies as a young
man before he became a Christian he went
through various
flirtations and involvement with
alternate systems of thought for a while
he joined the manichaean movement and
then became very much engaged with
neoplate neoplatonic philosophy which he
then rejected and spent much of his life
offering a critique against neoplatonism
though students of Augustine to this day
sometimes criticize Augustine for
thinking that he never really completely
rid himself of some of the rudimentary
ideas that were found in the very system
with which
he was contending now in addition to the
philosophical controversies he was
engaged in he was engaged also in many
theological controversies the two most
important of which are the so-called
donatist controversy which was a
controversy regarding the legitimacy of
baptism that had been performed by
Heretics or lapsed clergyman and so on
but even more important was his
controversy with the British monk
Pelagius and so we have that historic
so-called pelagian controversy in which
the doctrines of Grace were at the
center in fact Augustine's emphasis on
the grace of God in Redemption was so
strong
that he has been called historically by
the Roman Catholic Church the Dr grazia
that is the doctor of Grace but our
basic concern here is not with this
theological contributions of of which
there are many and they are vastly
important but where he fits in the
history of Philosophical Investigation
now one of the most and one of the most
important things that he was concerned
about was the question of epistemology
and of the
problem of epistemology that had been
developed by neoplatonic thinkers
and Augustine was facing a Revival of
skepticism in his own day and that
skepticism
really was two-pronged on the one hand
there was a widespread skepticism
against the reliability of the senses or
the reliability of sense perception in
order to gain any knowledge
and also there were those Skeptics who
were completely skeptic about our
ability are skeptical about our ability
to
achieve Truth at all
and Augustine countered these people by
saying
that even the skeptic who is completely
skeptical has to admit to certain truths
if he says that no truth is possible
then he's already committed himself to
the discovery that one truth is
discoverable namely the truth that there
is no truth discoverable you hear the
same kind of language in our culture
today in popular armchair philosophy
where people say there are new apps
there are no absolutes except of course
for the absolute that there are
absolutely no absolute so Augustine did
that sort of thing of turning the
Skeptics on their ears
and pointed out that even in their
skepticism they couldn't escape one
principle of epistemology namely the law
of contradiction
because they depended upon the law of
contradiction for their skepticism
and if one is going to reason at all
they are dependent upon rational
principles and this was one of the
points that he tried to make but he's
his major concern was how we can avoid
skepticism and rise to certainty
because the whole issue of philosophical
certainty has been one of the things
that is preoccupied the theoretical
thinkers of Western history can we sure
can we be sure of anything and of course
one of the first targets of the question
of certainty
is sense perception
and this will be a problem that will
continue in philosophical inquiry up to
our present day
and the fundamental problem with sense
perception is that we already are aware
that our senses
are not perfect
that we can have distorted perceptions
of external reality
and since it's possible for us to have a
distorted view of the world around us it
makes basing truth or basing certainty
in any way Upon Our sense perceptions
something of a serious philosophical
problem
now
Augustine was not ready to put sense
perception at the highest level of
certitude by any means but nor was he
prepared to Simply jettison sense
perception as a useless Enterprise he
understood something fundamental to our
humanity and that is that our only
transition our only link to the world
apart from our own interior minds and
our own thinking is our body
our bodies are the links that we have
with the external world I have no way to
get in touch with the external world
except by either seeing it hearing it
tasting it touching it smelling it and
so I am dependent upon my senses to have
any information
coming to me from outside of the
Interior chambers of my own mind
now if that vehicle of knowledge
is completely untrustworthy
then of course I have no way of knowing
for sure about anything outside of my
own thinking
so Augustine took a close look at that
problem of sense perception and one of
his famous
illustrations was the illustration that
was common to people in the ancient
world and one that I think all of us
have experienced at one time or another
if you've ever been in a rowboat and you
put the ore in the water
and you look from the perspective of
sitting there in the row boat you look
at the ore and of course you can see the
handle of the ore until it goes into the
water but if the the sky is bright and
the water is clear enough you can then
see further down into the water and see
the end of The Ore but from your Vantage
Point it looks like once the ore hits
the water
it bends
do you recall that kind of sensation
where from the vantage point of being
out of the water you put the water you
put the ore in the water and from where
you're sitting you look and the uh the
blade of the oar is bent away from you
and so looking at that you would say
well I have a bent ore in my hands
is the ore really bent
or is this an illusion caused by the
water and and the light and all of that
well if it is an illusion and if such
Illusions are part of our daily
experience of perception
how do we know that all of our
perceptions are not Illusions well
Gustin made a very simple distinction
here but it's one that's very important
not just at a theoretical level but at a
practical level
he said well I may be wrong
about
what the ore is actually doing
but I still can be confident
that I am perceiving
the or
as being bent that is the content of my
perception
may not be perfectly accurate but I can
still know
that I'm having the perception the
perception and that I am perceiving
that the ore is bent
now again that may seem like an
insignificant thing but so often for
example we in the clergy have to
moderate disputes between people or an
argument between a husband and a wife
and you get into these discussions where
you hear he says and she says and and
there's a difference of opinion as to
what transpired between them or what
actually happened and I know when I get
into those positions which are not very
enviable positions to be to play the
moderator in such disputes I say okay we
don't just have one question here
we are arguing about what happened
or about what was said and maybe we
don't have any record of what was said
in terms of a tape of it and it's your
word against his or so on
but we know this that something was said
and you differ as to what was said
so that's one problem that we have to
get at
what was said is part of the actual
reality
but that's not the only thing you're
dealing with you're also dealing with
the perception of the reality
I may say to you
I don't believe that's what you said
I may be lying about that but I may
actually have an error in my my memory
or whatever but I actually believe
that you said something different from
what you say that you said
so that my perception of what happened
differs from yours now some people the
relativists come back and say well
that's the only truth there is the truth
of perceptions and so something can be
and not be at the same time in the same
relationship if you said that it didn't
rain and I believed it did rain well
it's true that it both rained and it
didn't rain at the same time in the same
relationship no
it either rained or it didn't rain
but what is both true here in in this
case is you believed that it rained I
don't believe that it rained
so we both though we have differing
perceptions the content of the
perception
is part of the reality
that is let's say that the reality is
reality x objectively
and we disagree as to what that reality
is we have why and we have Z
two different perceptions of x
now that there are two different
perceptions
are part of the reality and that's the
second aspect that we have to deal with
in debate and in disputes but then
there's a third element that's always
important to human relationships and
that's how we feel
about the perception so you're dealing
with two people that are angry with each
other so I got three realities what
happened
is the first one the second one was how
what you perceive to have happened and
the third one is how you feel about what
you perceived to have happened and so it
becomes very complicated
now Augustine is probing this sort of
thing and he says
a man
who has
just come out of the shower
and steps into an air-conditioned room
says oh it's cold in here
where the other man
who has
uh
stepped off an iceberg walks into the
room and says it's warm in here well is
it warm or is it cold
we don't perceive color the same you
like tomatoes I don't like tomatoes can
we agree the tomatoes taste good well
they don't suit my taste but they do
suit your taste
and even though we may not be able to
agree on the objectivity of the taste or
of the color or of the degree of heat or
coldness we can still have awareness of
our perceptions
now so Augustine is trying to avoid full
skepticism and to reconstruct what we
will see later in the history of
philosophy the important Assumption of
the basic reliability of sense
perception
without which as I said you have no
access to the external world
but Augustine did not rest with sense
perception because he recognized that
there was a difference in terms of the
level of certainty that can be achieved
between
sensory experience and what we might
call today the formal level of knowledge
or rational truths
or to make it simple mathematical truths
we can be certain
that three and three are six
and they will always be six and they
have always been six we're not talking
about three apples and three apples
we're talking about the formal concept
of the relationship between the number
three as it is added to another number
three and to the sum of the two which is
six which is simply a form of symbolic
logic
when we reduce mathematics to that point
so following Plato and his theory of
forms and so on Augustine agreed that
there is a higher kind of certainty that
comes from the mind or the soul from
rational truth
but he was by no means a simple
rationalist in the sense that he thought
that the only truth that could be
learned would be that truth which was
deduced by naked human reason
rather
the highest level of certainty
he was concerned to find not as an
abstract philosophical goal but
Augustine was very much concerned about
human happiness
but not in the level that was found
among the stoics and the epicureans who
were just looking for philosophical
peace of mind
but really what Augustine was searching
for was the Supreme happiness of the
Soul
that is found in beatitude
a beatific happiness
and I put quotes around the word
happiness when I talk about Augustine
because we have such a cheap use of the
term happy we talk about happiness as a
warm puppy or happiness is making a
birdie on the green no no for Augustine
the ultimate happiness is a knowledge of
God
and that more than anything else was
what he was searching to discover
now in the process as an apologist he
worked out certain Arguments for the
existence of God
but what he was basically saying was
this that in the first instance
if the Mind recognizes that certain
truths are objective
necessary and eternal
such as the truths of mathematics such
as the truths of logic
the formal truths of which I was
speaking a moment ago
that there must be according to
Augustine
an immediate recognition that there has
to be some foundation for these Eternal
truths there has to be some source of it
and he of course believed as a matter of
Faith at this point that the ultimate
source for truth and for all Eternal
truth is an eternal being who eternally
thinks his perfect ideas now you can see
the little touch of relationship here to
Plato and his theory of ideas
but he says that if any truth is eternal
such as the truth two and two or four or
three and three and six
or six that that implies
a knowledge
of God that doesn't mean that that gives
you a personal relationship with God
but rather we get in touch with the
content of God's Own thoughts
that is for Augustine you can deny God
religiously but you can't deny him
philosophically if you allow for Eternal
truth because by getting in touch with
eternal truth you're getting in touch
with the Eternal mind you may be hostile
to that mind you may be unreconciled to
that mind but you are
dealing with that mind as long as you
are dealing with formal truth now again
Augustine is also important for calling
God the great illuminator
who he used the analogy is just this
light of some sort sunlight or whatever
is necessary for us to be able to
perceive things in the external world if
I'm cast in the pitch Darkness I can't
perceive anything with my eyes without
the added extra benefit of the light so
for Augustine the mind can know nothing
except insofar as God himself functions
as the great Illuminator now one once he
gets to his concept of God he turns his
guns with the Vengeance on neoplatonism
because part of the problem with the
neoplatonous and and other Greek
philosophers was that they saw the world
as a necessary extension of the being of
God
denying
the free voluntary work of creation
by God
and leaving them caught up somehow in
some or other form of pantheism and so
it was Augustine who really developed
the Christian concept of creation X
nihilo
creation actually hello but God creates
the universe freely and voluntarily out
of nothing
what he means by that is not to violate
the Cardinal scientific rule ex nicoloni
he'll fit out of nothing nothing comes
he doesn't mean to suggest that there
was some nothing that God then shaped
into something but he's talking about
the unique power of God to bring
something into being that previously did
not exist
and he alone has the power of being to
do that and the way in which he does it
according to Augustine is through what
he calls the Divine imperative
or the Divine Fiat in this case Fiat is
not a little car in Italy but it is the
command that God has the power to say
let there be
and by virtue of the sheer creative
power of this one who is the Eternal
source of all being
that he can bring something into being
that previously
was not